[inaudible]
你好 欢迎来到HSK汉语课堂 我叫於斌 我是中国人 你是哪国人
Can you tell me your country's name in Chinese?
你能用中文告诉我 你的国家的名字吗?
Yingguo? Hanguo? Aiji? Aodaliya?
英国 韩国 埃及 澳大利亚
In this lesson, we're going to learn how to count numbers
这节课 我们来学习中文中如何数数
and talk about people's ages in Chinese.
如何谈论人们的年龄
Follow me to read 1 to 10 please.
请跟我从1读到10
Yi, yi,
一[Yī, yī]
er, er,
二[èr, èr]
san, san,
三[sān, sān]
si, si,
四[sì, sì]
wu, wu,
五[wǔ, wǔ]
liu, liu,
六[liù, liù]
qi, qi,
七[qī, qī]
ba, ba,
八[bā, bā]
jiu, jiu,
九[jiǚ, jiǚ]
shi, shi.
十[shí, shí]
On top, the number is
最上面的数字 是
ling, ling.
零[líng, líng]
Wow, so many pandas.
喔 好多大熊猫
[inaudible]
大熊猫[Dàxióngmāo]
Let's read it.
我们来读
Yi, yi,
一[Yī, yī]
er, er,
二[èr, èr]
san, san,
三[sān, sān]
si, si
四[sì, sì]
wu, wu,
五[wǔ, wǔ]
liu, liu,
六[liù, liù]
qi, qi,
七[qī, qī]
ba, ba,
八[bā, bā]
jiu, jiu.
九[jiǔ, jiǔ]
The last picture,
最后一张图 是
shi, shi.
十[shí, shí]
Numbers above 10 are easy to remember,
十以上的数字很好记
you just say ten one, ten two, et cetera.
你只要说 十一 十二 以此类推
Shi yi, shi er.
十一 十二[Shí yī, shí èr]
Let's see some more numbers.
我们多看一些数
Read the list with me, please.
请跟我读这个列表
Shi yi
十一[Shí yī]
Shi er
十二[Shí èr]
er shi
二十[èr shí]
er shi san
二十三[èr shí sān]
san shi si
三十四[sān shí sì]
si shi qi
四十七[sì shí qī]
wu shi liu
五十六[wǔ shí liù]
liu shi jiu
六十九[liù shí jiǔ]
qi shi ba,
七十八[qī shí bā]
ba shi wu,
八十五[bā shí wǔ]
jiu shi jiu.
九十九[jiù shí jiǔ]
How do you ask someone's age in Chinese?
如何用中文问某人的年龄呢?
Here is a video for you.
这里有一个视频
[inaudible]
>> 旭东 你多大了? [Xùdōng, nǐ duō dà le?] >> 我二十四岁 你呢? [Wǒ èr shí sì suì. Nǐ ne?]
Did you hear the age of these three people?
你听到这三个人的年龄了吗?
er shi si
二十四[èr shí sì]
er shi yi
二十一[èr shí yī]
shi ba
十八[shí bā]
ni duo da le?
你多大了? [Nǐ duō dà le?]
How old are you?
你多大了?
Ni duo means how old.
多大[duō dà] 意思是多大
Le is used at the end of a sentence to indicate change of state.
了 用在句尾 表示状态的转变
In other words, there's now a new situation or there is about to be a new situation.
换句话说 现在有个新情况 或者将要有个新情况
Si means year.
岁 指年龄
For the answer to the question,
对于 你多大了[nǐ duō dà le?] 这个问题的回答
you say, Wo, plus your age and then say,
你说 我 加上你的年龄 然后加上岁
read after me please.
请跟我读
Ni duo da le?
你多大了 [Nǐ duō dà le?]
Wo er shi si sui.
我二十四岁 [Wǒ èr shí sì suì.]
Ni ne?
你呢[Nǐ ne?]
Wo er shi yi sui.
我二十一岁 [Wǒ èr shí yī suì.] 我二十一岁[Wǒ èr shí yī suì.]
Ta duo da le?
他多大了 [Tā duō dà le?]
Ta shi ba sui.
他十八岁 [Tā shí bā suì.]
Have you noticed there is a ne after after ni? What is it?
你注意到了吗 你的后面有个呢? 这是什么?
Ne is a participle which can be used to ask reciprocal questions,
呢 是一个助词 用来进行回问
also known as bounce-back questions.
或者叫 弹回问题 (bounce-back questions)
Ne can be used to form simple questions asking what about or how about.
呢 用来组成简单的问题 询问是什么 怎么样
The structure is, topic plus ne.
结构是 话题加上呢
For example,
比如 你多大了 [Nǐ duō dà le?]
Wo shi liu sui. Ni ne?
我十六岁 你呢? [Wǒ shí liù suì. Nǐ ne?]
Wo er shi qi sui.
我二十七岁 [Wǒ èr shí qī suì.]
Ni shi na guo ren?
你是哪国人? [Nǐ shì nǎ ɡuó rén?]
Wo shi Zhongguo ren.
我是中国人 你呢? [Wǒ shì Zhōnɡɡuó rén. nǐ ne?]
Interestingly, the pronunciation for he is the same as for she.
有趣的是 他的发音和她是一样的
So, when I say ta,
因此 当我说 TA[tā]
you actually don't know if I'm talking about him or her.
你不知道 我说的是他还是她
That is really tricky, isn't it?
那真的挺麻烦 是吧
However, in writing we don't have this problem because they are different characters.
不过 在写作中就没有这个问题 它们用的是不同的字
Have a look, ta, ta.
看一下 他 她[tā, tā]
Now, let's do an exercise.
现在 我们做个练习
Listen to three statements.
听下面三个陈述
The question is how old are they?
问题是 他们多大了?
Number one. [inaudible]
第一个 他叫奥巴马 他五十四岁 [Tā jiào Àobāmǎ. Tā wǔ shí sì suì.]
Number two. [inaudible]
第二个 她叫章子怡 她三十七岁 [Tā jiào Zhāng Zǐyí. Tā sān shí qī suì.]
Number three. [inaudible]
第三个 他叫林书豪 他二十八岁 [Tā jiào Lín Shūháo. Tā èr shí bā suì.]
Okay. Can you tell me [inaudible]?
好 你告诉我 他们多大了? [Tāmén duō dà le?]
Okay, let's see the answer,
好 我们来看答案
Obama [inaudible] Obama, wu shi si qui.
奥巴马多大了? 奥巴马五十四岁 [Àobāmǎ duō dà le? Àobāmǎ wǔ shí sì suì.]
Zhang Ziyi, [inaudible] san shi qi sui.
章子怡多大了? 章子怡三十七岁 [Zhāng Zǐyí duō dà le? Tā sān shí qī suì.]
The last person,
最后一个人
Lin Shuhao  [inaudible] er shi ba sui.
林书豪多大了? 他二十八岁 [Lín Shūháo duō dà le? Tā èr shí bā suì.]
Did you get it?
你明白了吗?
We have learned so much today.
我们今天学了很多
Have a good rest.
好好休息
Xiexie!
谢谢 再见